[Music]
hello and welcome to the junkyard love
what's up guys welcome to the junkyard
love podcast today's recommendation due
to the current release date of the
podcast we're currently at the beginning
stages of the coronavirus situation so
I'm going to recommend something that
came up actually today on coronavirus
but it's gonna apply for any time that
this is listened to it's about fear this
is a clip on Tom bile use impact Theory
the title is behavioral neuroscientist
shows you how to break the coronavirus
anxiety cycle by Judson Brewer it's
fantastic I just finished let's do it
before I finished up editing this
episode so it's fresh my mind but it's
great to learn about fear you know
understand it apply the scientific
method to the fear that you're
experiencing right now or you my
experience in the future understand it
you can tackle it with stuff like this
so check that out that's on YouTube
behavior your behavioral neuroscientist
shows you how to break the coronavirus
anxiety cycle Judson Brewer Tom by oles
is the YouTube account today we've got a
Kelly st. Onge he's a good friend of
mine so happy for you guys to meet him
and hear his view on the world
drink some water sit upright let's go we
have chia dog Kelly
st. Onge in the house man I'm happy to
have you on we just kind of went over
the subjects that we're gonna try to
touch on today I'm hyped I think it's
perfect we write it we did have a
podcast before but it was I'll probably
still post it of course but we didn't
really like talk too much into this and
I just think that knowledge is so much
power and every way so I think just
learning about things you know a lot of
ink actually about
in this podcast this morning about the
scientific method it was a it was just
like a 45 insert from how stuff works
but uh and I was thinking about it like
if I had to correlate it to my human
emotions like how have I used a
scientific method you know I was
thinking when I was like I'm gonna I'm
gonna heal my depression I'm gonna get
better like I'm sick of hurting I'm
gonna do this like I did I use a
scientific method I was like what's
going on what do I do here like you kind
of start testing it you start
troubleshooting right oh yeah perfect
yeah yeah so yeah I don't know I just
thought it was integrated entered my
head so I figured out I'd bring that up
at the beginning so yeah that's perfect
because that goes right into oh oh and
I'll get there too but that goes into
exactly what we're gonna do today
perfect yeah so any listeners what we're
gonna do today we're going to dance
around a few subjects that all correlate
we both have a little bit of things
written down so we'll try to maybe loose
and fun of course we're just kicked back
here hanging out of the studio but we
are going to try to not dumb down I hate
that sentence of course not dumbed down
but just kind of conceptualize some
things around math and in science and in
quantum physics and in all these things
which I know that sounds intense so if
you if those things are hurdles to you
just I I trust us just stick around and
just just if you hear a sentence that
doesn't make sense just keep listening
and then a little loop back yes it's
something I have listened to I listen to
a lot of air Quine science podcast the
portal I always send you those I'm
always like Kelly you're my math friend
like do you think about this concept
that guy's so brilliant is so smart but
he said that too at the beginning one of
his podcasts I think that's kind of what
I do have to do it like sometimes I
float away for like a minute while he's
talking and I'm like oh no first yeah
then I come right back and it seems like
it make sense oh yeah and just bear with
us I think it would be an exciting fun
conversation happy to have you Kelly
yeah yeah thanks for having me
yeah heck yeah so I kind of wanted a I
really wanted to create a podcast with
you that I've I've been doing or having
to study for the last couple years here
and we're gonna go over basically we're
gonna go over computers
and we're gonna go into computers
quantum computing we're gonna do a
little bit of math stuff we're gonna go
into AI and we're all gonna kind of very
nicely thread all this little tangle
them together yes and yeah so I'm gonna
start with you know computer is kind of
like this magic box right everybody kind
of has idea of okay this is a computer
it has a screen it has a mouse has all
these things that a keyboard and such
and yeah I'm gonna go right into it so
the computer has this has what's called
layers of abstraction so on the very
bottom level is a is very complex and
yet very not very abstract and that's
the the very layer of physics so it goes
in it will go into as we get higher it
will become less complex and become more
abstract such that let's say like others
you walk into a room and you see a bunch
of lights like bunch of light switches
all in a room and you think well what
are these light switches do there's no
lights there's no what do they do right
so that's you walk into a room and you
just really don't know what you're doing
whereas when you have when you get to
the highest level of abstraction less
complexity you have you will be able to
walk into a room and you will be able to
say oh I know that these things do this
so if I turn on the light lights turn on
so that's kind of what what happens but
I'll go into more of the light switch
analogy here in a little bit so so yeah
on the very bottom level of this
abstraction there's the physics level so
you know it has to do with electrical
current going to a switch
on turning off okay as we go higher we
have what are called bits and these are
important because what I'll get back to
these later when it comes to quantum
computing so so a light switch is kind
of like one bit you can turn it on turn
it off right so binary so the net that's
that's where the binary level comes from
it's the it's the set of instructions
that a machine can understand we cannot
understand can you understand so if you
see like a wall binary Jake can you
understand any of it yeah okay I mean
either can I like it's it's something
that the computer does understands
really really fast that's the other
thing about computers people will go oh
well I got a smartphone I got I got a
laptop that does all those cool stuff
for me well computers are really dumb
yeah yeah I said it Peters like dumb
[__] Alexa I'm sorry so don't don't hurt
me oh my god no way
yeah this can I got one sitting here
okay yeah no how are they dumb so
computers are dumb because I mean
literally Mike I have mine right Ropin
right here right
it hasn't really done anything it's not
like you and I are having a conversation
right now and I'm trying to explain the
layers of abstraction and computing to
you in such a meaningful way whereas my
computer all it's done it's just it's
just sat here and waited for me to do
something right yeah it's doing nothing
until you until you interact with it
until you tell it what to do I mean and
they and then in such it's not like it
intelligent figures out these from the
magic universe problems it answers
questions that it's already been given
it's its it has answers if this than
that right yes correct it's correct
you're a hundred percent correct so so
on the other hand the thing is is that
humans and I hate I mean I hate to say
it but humans are actually compared to
computers are really smart meaning we
can have we can extrapolate
ideas we can communicate between each
other here we can do all the stuff the
only thing that is is that we are really
slow humans are really slow when it
comes to crunching numbers or doing
repetitive tasks or things like that
whereas computers are really fast so
when you decide to bring those two
together you get something that's just
really amazing you know so just like you
said I mean you're you're you're kind of
in this higher level of abstraction the
if-then statements that and I'll get to
that in a little bit and also get to
what's known as debugging - I mean you
actually injured in intro to that in
your introduction but so anyways back to
bits so there's just like the light
switches in the room so each light
switch is a bit and usually it goes and
powers of two it can go in three but you
don't want to so if you had four light
switches in a room that's four bits that
the number of different ways you can
assign that light switch is sixteen
different ways so I think of like one on
and the rest off and then the next one
on the second or the second one on the
first one off yeah yeah so it's ^ in is
the formula but uh yeah and you might
have seen it just messing around with
like Ableton and stuff usually the
architecture or the the bus address for
for programs like 32-bit 64-bit right
things like that that has to do with
with with that right yeah okay I just
jump the gap there yeah cool so so let's
say you were to walk into this room and
you see six of row 64 light switches and
you go okay well I can actually
meaningfully turn these light switches
on such that I can get a desired effect
well
one of the cool things is that you can
actually assign the the farthest row of
light switches or the furthest light
switches from the left to do to be an
instruction so let's say and it's all so
like let's say you divide each these
light switches into eight sort of thing
so if you had one one light row of light
switches does this this thing and
another row of light switches is the
next bit the next bit the next bit so
let's say you wanted to add
you know 120 to 280 something like that
well you'd actually assign the first
that first row bits that on the very far
left you can actually say okay I want to
tell to say that okay if you if you were
to say I want to make the firt the the
third light switch the is so it's zero
one zero zero and then the remaining
bits for the number I want that
instruction to be known as add so then I
can have 16 different operations where
it's like I want it I want it to do I
want the information that's coming in to
do what I wanted to do so I wanted to
add or I wanted to subtract or I want it
to multiply I can have 16-bit I could
have sixteen instructions doing whatever
I want to the following binary numbers
so you have the so in these light
switches you have at the beginning it's
just like an on or off yes or no oh yeah
so it works from from from left to right
it the it's all separate into 8/8
because it's it's it's eight bits but
there's so eight bits is a word and then
four four bits is a byte right and then
two bits
let's what's what's less than a byte
Jake
okay so when you when you take a little
bit of a bite what is that it's a nibble
actually I don't know what the trick is
who ever got to that was like like
science let's make it cute okay okay so
I was trying to just visualize the the
light switch so it's essentially like
these light switches do this but what
you're saying is you can program these
light switches you can program the first
eight to say when I want to add or I
wanted to do this yeah so so in order us
to in order for us to get to the other
56 light switches if we have 64 the
first eight are now designated to tell
the signal what to do as it gets to the
other way yes that's you got it yep cool
okay people are following along and I
think that kind of makes sense that's a
good job so yeah great job so you walk
into this room and you're like but that
can be you don't want to just okay I
want to add two numbers right I don't
want to flip on all these dang light
switches all right that just can I get
like something like a robot or some
something else to do that for me and so
that's that's where the next layer of
abstraction comes in okay so as we
getting hired we're getting we're
getting more what if I were to have like
a magic wand that does this for me I
hate to use a magic wand but let's say I
had would you though yeah I would love
but let's say like I had or let's say I
had I could give it a command that says
okay well actually I want I want you to
move this bit of data into this register
and do this and do that and then add
them together without having to turn all
these damn light switches on that that
is actually called assembly so you're
actually moving outside of the hardware
side of things and you're moving into
the software side of things so where
that assembly language will allow you to
give it give those commands your give
give the command to that that first
register of light light switches to say
okay I want you to move this or I want
you to add this or I want you to
subtract this the only
part about assembly is is it still is
very tedious and not not something that
we want to say okay move it bit by bit
by bit by bit a bit kind of thing where
as or because because you literally have
to go you have to go okay I want you to
load in my class what I've learned is
you have to go okay I want you to load
zero into the register one are the the
want the first register that I want you
to then move the value of two into that
register and then I want you to load
another register or I want you to load
another zero into another register and
then move that register or move another
number into that register and then I
want you to add these and then I want
you to put it in another register see
how that kind of gets just yeah it's so
many layers - yeah you were the way I
was visualizing is actually kind of like
a tree what was the tree we're talking
about like just I mean with fractions
where you just oh the fractal or the I
mean yeah but if you can think of it I'm
sure you see it in your mind like that
you visualize it like that
it's just things that seem so in depth
right it's kind of a simple task really
right it is a super simple job simple so
for a computer to get you get to a
computer get to A to Z all I have to do
is do these quick little trees in its
head you know yeah yeah so to speak yeah
so but as we're going up so I even gets
even higher than that so this is where a
lot of kids in their seat are computer
science program they actually start in
C++ which is the first or it's not the
first it's called an object-oriented
programming but it's not the first one
um but it's the it's pretty much the
main one it's it's kind of like I'd like
to equate it to like learning piano
first mmm you know how like getting
music Yuri yeah if you if you start on a
piano first it's almost like you can go
anywhere like I've noticed like you hope
that's true
oh is it is so true it's so true I I
believe it yeah I mean I feel like I'm
understanding music and in rhythm in a
new way I was just
I'm talking about this student it's a
new language it's a weird thing like it
the more I learned piano the more I'm
getting like a little progressing in
penis it's it's a it's hard to put into
words because there's not a word
language I suppose but it's a kind like
learning music is just there's a
different language for sure
so as we get into this higher
programming language it's less abstract
so I as a programmer could come in and
say okay I want this program to do
exactly this and then what will happen
is when I get everything completely
right when I'm done with it we'll do
what's called it compiles the code but
what it's doing is it's breaking down
the code that I just wrote into assembly
and then from assembly it breaks it down
into that machine code for such that the
computer can understand it right so
eventually as we get even higher we get
into the the end result of it or the
highest level of the abstraction which
is the which is the user interface it's
it's such that you or anybody could walk
into a room and go okay I know exactly
what to do here I know to put a two here
put a plus sign and a two and then hit
go and it's gonna give me the answer for
right so or even rather and tell me if
I'm wrong I might be jumping too far
it's basically when it jumps to user
interface it's basically taking those 64
switches and making it one switch and
all you have to do is walk it and hit
the switch
no ok all right back me up then okay I
got lost so okay so it's your so the 64
light switches are still there but now
there's like there's like a it's like a
plugin it's like you put let's say you
put a machine over the top of this of
these 64 light switches right and then
you can tell that you can then tell that
machine okay I have these command sets
that you can do such that I don't have
to go around and
turn on all these 64 light switches
right the machine does it for me so that
those layers are just added on machines
to wear it will tell the the previous
speech are the Machine below it hey do
this right yeah so okay so I kind of was
I think I kind of was right there so I
usually turn getting 64 switches into
one switch that part yeah yes kind of
yes the human isn't interact in the
human retina walking in the room at this
point races right yeah usually you're
interacting with yes exactly so it's
it's it's boiling all down to something
that you can understand as a human
whereas walking into a room and seeing a
wall of 64 light switches is like what
do we do here you know where do I start
so yeah anyways so that's those are the
layers of abstraction that you go
through and a lot of what happens in the
C program or a C++ to get from - well
how do you how do you get from A to B
inside that program well there are
different different algorithms that you
can take and an algorithm is just
something is just an instruction set
it's like like if you look on the back
of a Nestle Tollhouse chocolate chip
package it will tell you okay you need
salt you need flour you need all this
stuff and then you do this and then you
do this yeah and then compiling is
actually kind of like baking them in a
way if you if you really think about
okay so to get to the final problem yeah
to get to the the final thing it
compiles so like baking in would be but
but programming everything is making
sure that the algorithm is just an
instruction set that's all it is right
so when you're going through your
instruction set you have an idea of okay
well how do how do I you know how do I
use combinational logic to get to an end
result and that's that's kind of right
where you're at when you're talking
about the scientific method and how you
were you were basically debugging
yourself right yeah and debugging
debugging so what happens when you
program something and then you say you
decided to run right it'll actually
start the very beginning of yours your
program source key and go step right
through it until it it gets to the end
until you tell it to stop or it ends or
it does something or it hits an error
before I get to the end yeah semicolon
that's the bane of every program its
existence anyways yeah debugging is just
like that so I can I can set I can tell
different variables inside that
programming code I can go I can look at
them I can go okay I actually want so I
want you to kind of its debugging it's
kind of like a fake run of your program
so you could put certain like pause
points in a way so you put a pause right
here on your program and say okay at
this point in time what is this variable
doing and you can look at it and go okay
well I see that I put it into a for loop
and I got this loop going it's now at
the counters at six times I've gone
through this loop so you can say okay
well why if it's saying if I'm seeing my
output and it's getting into seven well
why is it getting to seven I can
actually put a little stopping point
like that and see what exactly it's
doing so that's that's kind of what
debugging is and so that's kind of kind
of like what you were saying is or even
the if-then statements so if I see that
like the logic I'm getting isn't quite
correct
I can go okay well I can step through
there there are if-then star if-else
statements in programming to say that
okay if if it is this then run this
protis code right saying okay but if it
isn't this then it needs to do the rest
of this code or it needs to do else if
it's conditional logic is what it is
right and you have more than two
variables there oh yeah you can have
anything you run there it's like if if
anything anything yeah oh yeah and then
there's there's also such there's also
things like case brakes
hmm so it'll check to see okay it'll
actually go it'll rotate through this
thing and say okay if it's zero do this
if it's one do this if it's to do this
or it could be like if if the if the
answer is Washington if it's that then
do this right and there's a default one
where it breaks out that's that's just
case breaks and just like stuff like
that yeah but but so even just that
there and that's the just mean it's hard
to understand 'pl it seems a little
silly but in a sense it is so simple it
is very simple oh yeah it's just you you
give it an answer in it or you give it a
problem and it says if I get to this
answer then I know what to do if I get
to this answer that I know what to do
yeah that's that's that's pretty much it
but from from the ground up yeah you
start with your bits and then you even
even even past those bits so the bits
are almost like inputs right and then
you have logical gates so there's an
angei there's an or gate there's X or
there's an x or there's there's like I
think eight different gates you can do
but these gates build up that what's
called a nail at the ALU see what's a
hail you forget that the actual actually
having Jamie look it up for it that's
Joe Rogan's like homie that works for
them he looks up all his [__] on this
arithmetic logic unit so okay okay when
you build up these gates you get the ALU
but then after the ALU you get the
actual CPU the little square thing in
the middle of motherboard that's their
CPU right it's not that's that's the
brain of your computer right there so
then after that you go up into assembly
so that's that's switching from the
hardware side which is your motherboard
into the software side of things and
then higher than that is the C code and
even like dynamic then we just let her
like scripting programs and stuff like
our scripting languages things like that
right yeah but how that so there's that
and then there's actual quantum
computers that are gaining that are kind
of kind of weird right so people talk
about quantum computers and they're just
like oh God like that's that's the end
of the world type of thing yeah where
what's uh what's it we did it what's
Rick and Morty's like vo on quantum
quantum computing and because I feel
like they they touch on quantum stuff
pretty well if like they lay it out
don't you think I mean like a oh oh like
the box thing like the the like I'm
gonna push this but the gleeble box or
something like that where they where as
like Rick's car dies and he has to go
into the the mini verse oh yeah yeah
yeah where he dives they're like you're
just my [__] car battery yeah yeah
the Google box or something like that
but uh but yeah we're like he builds a
universe inside a battery to tell these
people hey make free energy for ya and
they like have a whole existence they
think they're just like living this
whole world peace among worlds yeah Rick
that's great oh actually that's the show
I'm not gonna ruin it but like that when
they get way down in the teeny vers so
it's it the logic kind of wrote or the
the the part where Rick Rick talks the
Morty and then their genius scientist
talks to Rick the same way Rick talked
to Marty oh yeah and then you kind of
there's a little piece that you figure
out about Rick because if it's continued
so if it's continued like that you
actually find out a little bit about his
backstory about
so it's kind of it's kind of there's
these parts in Rick and Morty where it's
just like god that's [__] dark that
show is deep dude layers deep yeah I
think my favorite episode was the unity
episode because it shows the contrast
between science and religion and how
like it combines people or it makes
people like I'm not gonna go there but
it makes people hey we can go there on
this podcast okay we can yeah I guess
but it shows how like without religion
and people would tear themselves apart
over [__] having cone-shaped nipples
so it's like oh okay so I give it like
that's that's actually a good one of the
main reasons are a good reason why
religions is well I mean humans don't
humans aren't born with like a value
structure and sometimes I mean there's
there is a right and wrong that we feel
but we don't [__] understand it if
it's not sharpened so having a structure
of values let's generalize it as that
but yeah so okay but actually I'm gonna
seg with this really nicely so in the
time episode you actually see you see
Morty he splits the times like into a
bunch of pieces and they're like on the
screen they're like in there all in
different universes and stuff well
outside of like the garage was a bunch
of cats and it's Schrodinger's cat mmm
yeah so huh it's allusion to
Schrodinger's cat which kind of brings
us full back to full circle here about
quantum computers so sure here was this
physicist guy this is a very famous
story I feel like if you're interested
in in scientist world you've probably
heard this this term before yeah so sure
you use this is this guy or this
scientist physicist who had this thought
experiment that you put this radioactive
isotope inside a box and then you put a
cat in it and the thing is you close the
box and the
of it is you don't know whether either
the cat is alive or the cat is dead and
you don't know whether or not the cat is
dead or alive so when that happens so
it's basically like the cat is this is
this particle right this is photon
particle and it's in what's called super
super position to where we don't know
whether or not the cat is alive or dead
until we open the box and see this
[__] dead so far we can assume
we can assume that he's dead we actually
don't know it hangs in a 50/50 balance
or what you know I'm right logically I
guess that's not the right word there
about something yeah yeah it's in this
50/50 balance of whether it being alive
or dead and that has to do with
superposition and entanglement wait hold
on how did Schroder how does this what
was his exact experiment let's see I can
let's pull up his exact experiment is
that because that does round it out
that's a it's essentially saying I
remember as you look this up I'll say
from Silicon Valley that's a wonderful
show they have a situation where there's
essentially a they have a live webcam of
an eagle's nest or a bird's nest and
they were like waiting for their eggs to
hatch or something essentially and then
one of the characters in the show called
in said hey I think something's going on
their eggs haven't hatched so what they
were saying was oh and then they they
had a gentleman come and check on it he
checked on the the webcam oh yeah
checked on that the Eagles but so that
and then what happened is the gentleman
who was checking on this like thing and
in this forest you know he's checking on
this bald eagle in the camera he falls
and then so what they're saying what
they how they round about is they're
like well if you Jared who's a character
in the story if you hadn't called about
this then that man wouldn't have been in
this situation yeah that man wouldn't
have fallen to his death most certainly
because he observed it yeah so it's it's
kind of this whole it's it's a you know
it seems like a small story but it it
has this this wonderful way to
conceptualize a lot of what-ifs yeah
so just get a book over there you can
borrow yeah yeah we'll go into that
later if you want to matrix stuff yeah
well [__] it let's just go to do it no
cameras so yeah yeah Wikipedia's I kind
of got it right
so it's an interpretation of quantum
mechanics applied to everyday objects
the scenario represents presents a
hypothetical cat that might that may
simultaneously be both alive and dead a
state known as quantum superposition as
a result of being linked to a random
subatomic event that may or may not
occur a thought experiment is also often
featured in theoretical discussion
discussions of interpretations of
quantum mechanics see yeah it's it's
just it's observing whether or not the
cat's alive or dead so you get into so
when you look at particles and we split
these particles and I might go into CERN
later I'm not sure talk about certain
later okay so when you split these
photons they are both connected equally
so photons can actually exist two places
at once
crazy right but they have they have
really high energy states as why they
can blip in and out of existence real
quick which is [__] weird
yeah we understand that really well yeah
yeah don't I'm not I'm really trained on
classical physics and not quantum
physics so I know right enough to get by
to swim the waters of quantum physics
but I can't I'm not gonna dive deeper
than that right no and I wouldn't expect
you to I just like being able to these
words come up so often in there they're
going to be more and more in our normal
language you know we use science and
technology more and more so I think it's
cool that you're able to explain such
that you are
but entanglement is just this thing
where basically when you split these
photons they exist in in in to two
places at once so whatever so you can be
light-years away and these things are
still connected somehow it's it's crazy
yeah but I mean well it's not crazy
because space and time are all connected
linearly across the fabric of space so
yeah anyways these these particles are
tied together and if you were to observe
them or better yet like measure them you
don't have to it's not physically
looking at something it's actually
measuring it and say okay this this
particle is there positive or negative
or so this isn't like if I'm just like a
sneak up on it okay yeah yeah you're not
gonna sneak up on it so it's actually
it's measuring it it's measuring it yeah
saying saying this is this this is that
yeah correct
so until you actually measure this thing
that's it it will if you measure and see
okay that this this photon particle is
actually positive then it collapses that
entanglement and says okay this particle
is positive whereas it'll go back so as
soon as you're I think yeah so once it's
measured it's it's done its its
collapses into that thing whereas more
photons are out there and they're in
that superposition of either being of
either being it's like a coin it's okay
it's like a coin okay so think of like
you toss a coin up into the air you
don't know whether it's heads or tails
yet and it just keeps rotating and
rotating and rotating but until you clap
claps your hands around a rabbit stop
and look at it you don't know whether
it's heads or tails it is both heads and
in tails at the same time and also not
heads wait so is that yeah does that
ever get into any sort of like or is
that just a quantum statement that's not
the right way to use words but like it's
so it's it's not yes not just yet - no
but it's also maybe gosh man I was I'm
sorry that that was that was gonna be
some sort of there was a concept that
floated in my mind for a second know
that I was like this is a middle out
algorithm but I thought I was thinking a
bit as probably just comes back to if it
comes back I'll try to solve the problem
but yeah that's that's so basically when
you split that particle it's it has this
entanglement - and it's it's in that
superposition of being either heads or
tails positive or negative and until we
observe it it it it just it's in that
state of superposition so what does this
have to do with quantum computers well
we're going to go back to we're gonna go
back to bits in the light switches right
so we understand that we understand that
these light switches are zeros and ones
right but the problem then becomes okay
what so how do we use that quantum rail
to represent these zeros and ones well
there's really no way you can so the
these people they built this very
elaborate machines called quantum
computers and they use what's called
qubits and these qubits can be in
multiple states at once and they
actually use quantum gates like the and
or XOR or those kinds of combinational
gates to make the ALU in the cpu so the
problem with quantum computers are
really fast and that's that's the reason
why they're fast is that they can
actually use that super that the
superposition of those qubits to make
combinational data possible right so the
problem that why why why why don't we
see you know why don't we see quantum
laptops well the problem there is
is that we don't necessarily really
understand how to use the layers of
abstraction like how I how I represented
it in a normal computer it can't cross
that threshold of going from the
hardware side to the software side and
that's why like we don't see that
because quantum computers just a problem
with clones right this is a huge gap
right here but so clones we can like
okay we can make like it'll look exactly
like a human all the we measured the
exact amount of the insides but how it
got there like the whoa I mean I'm not
sure I'm not sure yeah carry on anyways
um so um let's see
oh the layers of abstraction yeah so
yeah the the quantum computers are
designed to do very specific tasks but
do them very quickly
very much more efficiently than a normal
computer does but the layer of
abstraction that it has isn't isn't met
by let's say there's the computers that
we know it to do so we can't actually we
can't really program this thing we can
only do very low-level calculations
really fast right so that's why I wanted
to get into so I'll make that segue and
I'll go into prime numbers so what so
the problem that we're facing with
quantum computers is that the decryption
that that we use normally is is
maintained by prime numbers so what is a
prime number well a prime number is
something that divides or is divisible
by 1 and itself you know if you look at
3 5 7 11 17 things like that those those
prime numbers right but the thing that
they do is they use really really really
big prime numbers I'm talking like all
you
bring up illegal primes right now and
I'll show you the Eco crimes yeah legal
numbers - you can't have this number or
they'll throw you in jail
isn't that crazy like it makes it it
doesn't make sense because it's like
it's just a number like I can actually
think of it right now if I wanted to
like wait how would you get her in jail
yeah I'll get to that in a minute
so yeah I know that [__] where's our the
nuclear codes no nuclear codes
but yeah so you look at see look at this
number and it's just this huge ass
number prime number so you can just
search so people in the church is this
what would you search how to write it
just a legal political prime number read
it but see actually this is actually a
good one too because it'll actually go
into kind of what I'm going to talk
about here in a minute
Oh in the comments they do yeah yeah so
it's a check along friend just google
reddit illegal prime number see what
pops up area and I don't think that this
is actually a prime number I think
somewhere in the sequence or no it's a
it's a zip file that that can lead to it
is what it is but I don't think that
this is actually it because I think they
somewhere in that sequence they changed
one number right
so that's crazy right it's like that
that one number makes it from prime to
not prime that's weird
but so what if what if you were looking
at that right there and it had the
correct number in it I think the FBI
would actually contact this person at
some point be like yo take that down so
here's the crazy thing is why why is
this thing so illegal so when when when
you're using decryption there's what's
called public keys so let's say you log
into your bank account your bank account
sends a key that has a one huge ass
prime number in it and I think baking
keys are something they have like a they
have a allotted amount of
'is that banks can use for our prime
number keys that people can use to
access their [__] but they want it to do
is they want it to match the R if I got
it right it's you want to so it's a
handshake right it's it's you saying
okay I got my login information I want
to make sure this is cure so they use
that prime number to say okay this is
actually the right thing we're good this
guy's good so the problem is is that
when you're trying like hackers right
when they're trying to figure out okay I
want to figure out what this guy's
banking thing is right so I want to
figure out okay I can factor big numbers
right and they use prime numbers for a
reason because it's only divisible by 1
and itself
so they use a prime number because it'll
sit there it'll go okay a computer can
factorize a million the number a million
into it's all it's different factors
really quickly but it does that by
guessing and checking and say okay I got
all the factors um I'm good but it'll if
you have a big big number like that it
goes I got a check all these and I got a
I got to make sure that this this comes
out right and it sits there and it sits
and spins and spins and spins it's it's
it's gears and goes and it just takes
forever for it to compute and eventually
I mean if you give it enough time it'll
it'll spit you out something but the key
is not I mean we're human we don't
dialed it right anyone got time for that
yeah hey so the use prime numbers but
the problem is the quantum computers
will be able to say [__] that we got it
like like quick like yeah instantly so
that's that's the main issue between but
the other thing is also the abstraction
levels to it too so anyways yeah that's
that that's how prime numbers comes into
play but the the coolest thing the
reason why those prime numbers are
illegal is I think back in the day you
know
actually in that reddit thread back in
the day
this DVD pirating was was huge it still
is huge but what people what the DVD
company and decided to do is put a crib
machine key yeah they decided to put
that encryption key on it so that people
couldn't just rip off their stuff just
like that you know so I think someone
somewhere figured out that it was was
this illegal prime number and what they
did was this they I think they sold the
go they went to a company to go hey I
got the I got I didn't know the
encryption key to this so what they did
was this this company was like okay well
well uh we'll pay you for this and we'll
use will use this encryption key inside
of our devices that will allow you to
bust open busts open this DVD and then
then pirate it or upload it to a web so
people compared it right I mean it's
brilliant right well the FCC it was like
that you can't do that like we're gonna
we're gonna throw you in jail but having
that encryption key are having these
legal prime numbers because the company
had it they undoubtedly had it like you
can crack open this their device that
strips strips the information inside a
DVD and it was there
it was brought as day like your [__] how
does it rights yeah so that's good just
looping that to the ingredients thing so
that's like knowing like so if the back
of your back of your thing says flour
apples and cornstarch and that's what
makes it it tells you exactly how much
flour it tell us exactly how much
cornstarch it tells you the ingredients
not not just the ingredients good but
how it [__] works it's like having
the secret union it's like having secret
yeah it's it's kind of like heaven the
well I guess not a super time but I was
thing about like also that you know
Kings back in the day they'd have like
their official stamp oh yeah like if you
open like this is from me and yeah me
and yeah there's no ring yeah
yeah I forget what the ex that's called
why am i what is that called and I
totally this is like my favorite
terminology world over here I should
know this
okay maybe it's not even a cool name but
but yeah it is it is like but it's like
having that it's having that special
stamp or a special ingredient that says
that you don't include it's like KFC you
know you don't what's what's the secret
herbs and spices you know like you have
ma the juice yes tell your business
model
maybe there is Kung Fu Panda boom you
know that's such a good movie a great
movie that's actually I actually just
watch that like the other day no [__]
Shaylee and I just watched it in London
lengthen two months ago yeah you know I
noticed I I mentioned that I was in
London like I just want people to know
that I was in London dude watch it
anyway how funny would it be so like you
know how in movies how they'll they'll
get like actors or voice voice actors to
redub the the actual thing but I imagine
it'd be so I mean Kung Fu Panda is in
English obviously imagine if it was like
in like like cockney
like English oh oh don't know see a
gradient see green your [__] yang
alright
[__] off when she was a sequin greedy
man [__] off I don't know God okay hey
you know what I do want to talk about
also more cockney that way okay I did go
to this I always just want to mention
this I went to this pub shayna any was a
it was a cockney a cockney I don't know
what he call him cockney singer who's a
cockney pub performer yeah but em what
do you do is so great like it was just
you go into this small pub and they had
and we were super hungry so we ate we
were like the people who were eating any
question eat but everybody just singing
along they have their pints like people
are just like spilling their beer
although it's like this fun like
everybody's singing and he's just in the
corner with a curled mustache singing
like cool Irish songs and cool you know
British songs that one denies that
but I've hunted year old pup songs yeah
dude it's just so fun it was so fun I
love mentioning that because you just
the the cockney pub thing but I do want
to talk about something that we touched
on right before this was a coolness real
quick because it equates to kind of
we're just worried with the quantum
computing yeah recently this is not
meant to be a scary thing but recently
Google has they've got their version of
the summit computer the quantum can oh
yeah yeah so there there's a
football-sized so here's the way that I
know and please correct me if I'm wrong
there's a football-sized computer I
think it's in California summit it might
not be in California but it's
essentially its football sized computers
it's racks of computers inside a
warehouse or whatever that are just
solving problems it's just solving the
[__] problem of problems the problems
that you don't know exists or think that
we need to know it's looking in those up
and it's trying to figure them out and
whatever that's my understanding so my
in what Google now has is recently
within the last couple months we thought
this was like 10 years out or something
but they achieved the fridge sized
version of that exact same thing
Jesus yeah that's scary yeah [__]
hell I mean in again I they did say
they're like oh and it's a hundred times
faster they said that too which is
creepy but I don't I don't know if all
these I don't think these things equate
across the board as much as they likes
in conversation you know they simply
like relate like oh it's the exact same
thing is the football field but smaller
like I don't think it's that simple but
quantum computing is a very interesting
thing yeah but still yeah supercomputers
supercomputers are different from our
soul different from quantum computers I
mean we asked but so super computers are
still a computer that is still going off
zeros and ones it's not going off with
qubits or anything like that but it is
very very very very so the super
computer hasn't even jumped into kono
competing um
well think of think of like quantum
computers as something people use as
very the use quantum beginning as for
very specific things like even though
these these super computers could
actually
now do the same processes the how all
has to do with what what you'd really
try to so the problems that so it really
depends on what you want to try to do so
if you want to like map genomes and
stuff like that I mean you'd almost want
to use a supercomputer to do that
because you're looking at mounds and
mounds of data like so you want to sift
through that and look look for things or
whereas quantum computing it will do
different things much quicker because it
doesn't have to rely on zeros and ones
it's it's that super position that it's
relying on right so mmm no it's actually
so even scary so I think supercomputers
run off of what are called flops so
there used to be used to be called used
to be called MIPS now millions millions
of something per second but it's
actually starting to get into what's
called xxo scale and it refers to
computing systems capable of at least
one exaflop or a billion billion
quintillion or it's a billion billion is
a continent calculations per second a
billion billion Jake per second our
brains don't even our brains think that
were like yeah I get that
your brains don't get that it's just
like the population what right yeah we
know what seven point six billion people
that's that's this many people our
brains don't understand the number but
MIPS is a cute version yeah yeah if I
want to name a cat MIPS actually want to
kit
yeah it's it's nuts because you we're
starting to get into when you have that
that crazy or that amount of of
calculations per second you're starting
to get into or you're starting to get
into the capacity of an of a neural or
what our brains could actually do so our
brains are still really really [__]
powerful yeah like but it's it's just
weird because you you were now starting
to really
get into the threshold of holy [__] like
we're starting to we will I mean I I
almost think that we will see what what
is called the singularity in our
lifetime Jake it's gonna I think so -
actually it's I mean and it's not a
matter of if it's a matter of when and
yeah I think it's yeah I think it's
gonna it's dude it's there's so many so
many things that like I think like you
you think you're like oh here's how
we're gonna get there and here's how
that's gonna happen but I feel like it's
gonna be like like we you know when
we've reached the singularity like
whatever the [__] that really means even
yeah like what like how it's going to
happen how how we're going to get there
and like when and the time for it like
it's gonna be so so far-fetched we're
gonna be like yeah it's something we
can't even think about right now no it's
it's gonna be a whole different language
so going going into that there I mean we
talked about AI their their most
shockingly talking about what's called
narrow there's two branches of AI
there's the ones that we know Alexa Siri
things like that and then there's that's
the narrow AI and then there's the broad
AI which is the spooky one and the
spooky one is something that will that
that is the singularity it will happen i
I hope in our lifetime you know weird I
know that's it's kind of messed up to
say that I want to see it in our
lifetime but because it's it is scary I
mean you got people like Elon Musk's
saying it's like summoning a demon and
it really is like something Indian
there's a lot of people who think it's
exactly so many and it could it could
spell disaster for humans mm-hmm just
not I think I think there's a lot of
blind optimism about it which but but
but I also think that like we're right
to be scared right but we can't stop
progressing it's this weird I don't know
I mean I'm not I'm not in I'm not even
at any like I'm not piloting any ships
towards this harbor by any means you
know I'm not solving any of these
quantum things myself so I don't know
it's it's all different different ones
but it's going to change a lot of the
way we do
yeah and I and you put so I mean I hope
of all you listeners have lists or watch
the mandalorian and if you haven't I'll
try and not ruin it but you know what
actually let's just just so you have an
open platform let's just say right here
if you have not seen the mandalorian on
the disney plus disney disney go out
someplace we are going to have some
spoilers here it's a wonderful show
we won't ruin it even even if we talked
about some things it's definitely
watching it's super [__] good so
demand oh he shows up to this guy his
name is quill names quill right we glue
something like that he's a farmer he
helps so the mando helps the farmer or a
farmer out by getting rid of these thugs
in the base and they kind of spark a
friendship and he's like kind of like
the only guy you can trust and in the
beginning of the of the series there's
other bounty hunter look going after
baby Yoda is an IG droid and it's just
just the thug killer dude goes in and
wrecks these fools yeah it's awesome
and then so this this IG droid was like
[__] this I'm gonna kill this baby Etta
and and Amanda was like [__] now I like
the baby out of [__] shoots the IgG
right in the head yep [__] dope right
so being as resourceful as this quill
guy is after the mando leaves this cool
guy picks up the IG droid and programs
it to two and then all that I looked
into the background of IG droids I
apparently like these things were like
as soon as they turn like they turned
them on they destroyed all the research
scientists yeah they just follow orders
yeah they just follow the orders do what
they're told it's a road so yeah so and
I'm and oh it showed him it was like a
very big like blaster shot to the head
in fact of his thing and they made it
clear that like destroyed his toes he's
done he's decommissioned so how does
this all apply well when so the mando
got into some trouble and he came back
to quill and was like yo in the mando he
doesn't trust droids though it's obvious
he doesn't trust droids he does
electrodes and he comes back to her
quill and the
next thing he sees is that here's this
IG droid back back in action and he's
like what the hell like yeah this
thing's a ruthless killer it's designed
to kill the baby Yoda like it's yeah I
don't like it like eff that like no way
he's like whoa whoa whoa he's like look
I I brought it back to my workshop i
reprogrammed it to do this I can
reprogram it to be a nurse droid like it
will serve me and it shows a whole cut
scene of quill teaching this IG droid to
to do certain things and it's it's a
warm scene to that they give you this
like okay we trust quill they give you
this like we understand man to our
character here but we trust we trust
quill with with this like changed this
yeah he changed this ruthless killer
droid into a functioning serving thing
to to operate into and to work with with
him instead of against him so
immediately I thought in the back of my
head like oh my god that is such a
reference to like how people look at AI
and he's like he goes look like it's the
programmer who programs this machine to
do the things that it needs to if it's
programmed to kill it will kill if it's
programmed to serve you into and to be
kind and to do these things it will do
that and so when when I talk when we
think about like the broad AI and people
he'll just doomsday thing and it's not
until it it can be like that and it it
might be like that I'm not sure but if
we put in measures in place to where we
see that okay like we we and it's tough
because we say that it's AI right but if
we control it's not really AI so what
what measures can we put in place to
make sure that it doesn't just end up
destroying us because if we go okay I
want you to I want you to
[Music]
or I want I want you to take control of
stock markets or whatever or whatever
you design to do how could you know if
at one point it decides okay well and it
could be just the most subtle little you
know snowball effect on something like
oh well this humans are now doing this
now I have to I have to protect what is
I'm designed for is to make sure that
this the system stays in place and is
balanced and does if I'm if I'm
threatened then I have to take care of
the problem which is humans that's
that's where it gets [__] up that's
right yeah so if you give it a just this
is over simplify to give it a task open
all the coca-cola bottles in the world
yeah like do that and the fastest way
possible go right now you give it a test
you're human you type you say this is
what you do toward go Lord goes but the
fastest way to do it because you said
the fastest yeah without these some
variables some laws let's say a robot
laws it's okay the fastest way to do it
is to kill all humans real quick and use
their fingernails to throw [__] you
know throw at the top of all the the
Pepsi cans or whatever I decide
Coco again the bottles it's yeah it will
find the shortest distance and it will
it's kind of cutting corners essentially
yeah without yeah not having any kind of
well actually what I should do is
gathered all the cool pins just pop them
off and isn't it doesn't do that yeah
it's like you said the fastest yeah it
was so fast yeah it's like what's I
still can't think of it we talked about
it but it's like what it's like
malicious web oh I almost like a half of
it it's malicious compliance is what
it's called complain and malicious
compliance it's like it's kind of like
your mom telling you to clean your room
and then moving everything outside of
your room such that there's nothing
inside right yeah like it's clean it's
clean it's kind of nothing in there and
clean it of all the
did the TV and everything that's I mean
that's like that's a great example of
malicious compliance it's very is that
that kind of lays out like it will find
the smallest thing I think that I heard
one thing but it's not malicious it's
just them making the connection right
yeah so that's the thing is I think that
you know as a basic human understanding
a lot of times we I don't know this for
sure but we might see it as like oh well
it's gonna it's gonna get human emotions
and do things maliciously yeah like it
no no it's not actually doing things
maliciously it's not like it picks up
the evil from the person who who
programmed it it's just the person who
programmed it told it to do these things
and if they didn't have the right checks
and balances it's gonna be contributed
as something evil yes it might kill
people but I mean yeah I mean that I
destroyed still went into that base and
murked fools but wait what was the the
part where he
so again spoiler mandalorian and the
part in the end worried the droid they
were in the boat thanks a lot yes love
about so remember at the end that was an
argument that that's a good example of
his programming actually which well an
interesting examples I don't think we're
don't think what he was doing in the
scene I don't think we're at yet right
technology was I don't think yeah it
gave they gave the demand oh the so
should I resort back to my old
programming or should you want to just
keep going yeah so I don't know
something like that but yeah it was
essentially saying like my what's the
most viable option to keep my main
programming like keep baby ode alive
what's gonna be the like sacrificing
myself as a droid is the most plausible
outcome to keep this baby out alive I
think it was like that but yeah but I
can't do it unless I'm told to resort
back to my main programming right yeah
dude yeah that just like that jarred in
the back of my head I was like that has
everything to do with like what's gonna
happen in the next how many ever years
as if we're gonna I hope to see it but
we definitely have to put protocols and
things in place and I don't know if that
means augmenting humans
with machines because it might it might
be that or it might be something else I
don't know I haven't gone that far in my
science career so but I'm pretty far but
I haven't gotten that far what is your
what are your class I think I asked you
nothing but what are your what are your
classes you two obviously C+ programming
oh dude I've taken two oh my god okay so
like just completely lame out okay
Oh like all of them are just computers
what have we develop it okay so how to
take three quarters of engineering
physics which is just going over the
classical physics I've had I started at
let's see I started at trig I placed in
the trig and then moved up to pre calc
and from those calculus as I made it
through calc 4 and then past calc for
I've done linear algebra and
differential equations for computing
I've done C++ is what they start yeah
it's it's basically as it's learning
piano for the rest of the computer
languages and then you going well I've
also done discrete math which is
learning about like numbers number
theory and number sets and like how
there's more than one infinite there's
like so there's a set of all numbers
right like normal numbers 1 2 3 4 5 but
how many numbers are in between how many
numbers are in between 1 & 2 there's an
infinite set of numbers between 1 & 2
and that's that's a different infinite
or the numbers of all all those numbers
inside that numbers is a different
infinite what was the aim of that class
discrete math concept is but if that's
the one where it's like it gets into
weird symbols I'll show you it gets into
like how what's that class was that oh
it was it was awesome I loved it because
it's like the guy who taught it his name
is Nick Macias he's a bit of a unicorn
down there at Clark I don't know why the
guys teaching he's just this he's the
kind of guy where you can tell because
you know
if you ever watch the Joe Rogan thing
even you see how like Elon sit there and
he'll like you can see that you can just
tell the gears are moving a mile a
minute I think he has 17 layers deeper
than a lot of us you know dude for real
some of us do with different depending
on your I don't know intellectual
ability you can hold you can hold layers
you know like this you can kind of get
to notice how many layers deep you can
hold a concept and be able to come back
to the original concept but dude that
guy [__] hold 17 layers anybody yeah
and this guy this Nick Macias guy he
could just you would ask him a question
and he was already like and the the
crazy part was he he wouldn't he
wouldn't necessarily look at you
straight in the eye mm-hm I don't know
if that's just like who is or just what
did it but you can just tell like the
gears in that guy's head are moving
right and I don't know why he was
teaching you but he taught it in such a
way it was really cool is like the
logical part of it was you know if like
if it's if you see water on the ground
you know doesn't mean it's raining
that's that was one of the questions
that got brought up there's water if you
walk outside and there's water in the
ground doesn't mean it's raining
I mean someone could be on the roof with
a hose someone could be up there pissing
on you it just depending xed to a spring
yeah so he you can beam it you have your
pipes just broke ten layers deep yeah
exactly that could be so many things
someone could one out there with a
bucket and just say I don't know but
it's it's it's learning that logic
system it's so if I said if I said A+
not be what is that equal hey yeah thank
you you got it great that's that's
exactly that's exactly it
but it gets much much higher than that
right yeah I mean think about telling
like all right all right computer who is
just ones and zeroes or whatever it is
like what yeah but you learn this yes
that's is so crazy but it's great it's
cool to think like you know just what I
said at the beginning
relating that back to like
problem-solving yep it seems like this
thing that science seems like this
out-of-reach thing or something that's
like oh it's not like my interest or
it's not like my I mean I see it's it's
all over in your life and you know I I
love science too but but I love
emphasizing to the regular people that
like do like the way that science is
done is how like humans work backwards
like you like you you figure so foul
perfect I do it it's it's perfect dude
you got that it's alright great I love
them so let me let me ask you this
or here's here's another question from
that guy that or Nick Macias and that is
a professor at Clark one of the things
he brings up is it's called mathematical
induction is the coin term of it but the
question is if you were to walk from
Cowell to Boston how would you do it you
have to walk ok this isn't it's not a
trick question
I mean I I suppose they would just just
plot the shortest distance there the
quickest distance from here to there
yeah but but how are you gonna do that
start walking
yes that's it you can get from Seattle
to Boston all you have to do put one
foot in front of the other that's
induction and it's it goes way deeper
than that because you have to prove it
and discrete math is doing that it's
it's okay prove that this number is even
and it's oh is it divisible by 2 if it
is then yes it is even if it's odd it's
2 n plus 1 so [__] like that it's
discrete math definitive in all cases or
is it it's discrete math something that
you could just keep taking semesters and
quarters of discrete math and learning
different layers and oh no it's just
it's just that one layer I promise it's
not like calculus ok I could say on the
surface right now I'm thinking that it
just complicates everything times no no
it's it's learning it's just number
theory and learning how how these
numbers interact we had a show there but
but the main point of it is yes you can
get from
you can get from Seattle to Boston but
how do you prove that and it's learning
okay well there is a road structure
there is a path to get there and it's
all it really is is putting one foot in
front the other yes
it's there's no there's no thing in the
middle where it's like haha like you get
to Missouri and you're like it's there's
no roads anymore
you're [__] so but yeah it's anyways
yeah that's that's discrete math okay I
don't know where we were going without
it I don't know I think we took a side
street oh it's asking you about that the
classes that you took Oh ask you to
expand on the screen oh yeah so it took
discrete what was what was your out of
these definitely stuff if you have more
because I think you definitely do but uh
if you can remember what was your like
funnest or I mean also like funnest
professors to you I was like pointing
out like the you know not like not to
like just make one person famous for
make them like but there is something
about pointing out someone's like named
this person this person was a good
professor because this yeah I always
loved doing that you know I mean besides
the core classes like English and stuff
like that like within the actual pour of
the engineering degree I mean I
definitely say that Nick yeah he's just
he reminds me kind of like a lot about
like you he was a very eclectic and his
choice of like suits that he wore like
he almost rivaled like you know the
crazy guy with the the question mark
suits and some yeah dude it was crazy he
would wear like those feather earrings
that you do that you have excellent yeah
I know right you would [__] click
with this guy so dude yeah awesome you
would love them do it what I'd sometimes
a daydream like maybe the podcast will
open up these cool relationships with
these like but you never know you never
know but uh ya know very eclectic guy
had just a beautiful way of explaining
things and I wish I could just follow
whatever he had to say but right it was
really cool because I think he really
liked I I had to do a special project
board about something and how to do with
music
and I think I wanted to
build a board that allowed me to connect
to
I think tractor and somehow program
tractor to that that little breadboard
just to do simple stuff not crazy [__]
just simple like play hip-hip yeah
exactly
yeah and he was just like oh that's
really cool like what like in he of
course this guy mile-a-minute right was
already like on my [__] about like oh
you need to do this ten layers deep
asleep and I'm like dude I'm trying to
figure this out myself hopefully so it's
just that yeah he was probably one of my
favorites but yeah I've taken C++ and
then from C++ you go to Java which is
the different object-oriented
programming language and then from Java
you go to you you keep you keep
programming and see but you go into
what's called data structures and you're
learning how different algorithms will
affect data differently then you get
higher I went into cs2 85 which is then
going into programming just called C so
clever clever play on words so CB c
programming language we can't came
before c++ so in a in a what's called
the for loop
you'd use assign an integer and each
side a is equal to 0
and if it's less than let's say 9 you
open an increase a and then you'll
execute some code so let's say inside
that code says your number is right so
you go through that code you start with
the first one right it's it starts with
0 a equals 0 and then it goes okay I'm
done with the loop I'll start back over
the loop ago okay now now now a is 1 and
then it goes in through the loop that
says okay your your number a is now
equal to 1 does it again is 2 is 3 a is
4 is 5 a 6 7 8
and then it gets to nine and then it's
done with the loop and it goes out so
what you do to tell aid to increase is
you go plus plus on the source code so
the funny bay so the funny programming
humor is see you came before C++ because
it's the next iteration of C code funny
right okay yeah dumb program oh that's a
force left stupid chili no I mean I
wasn't laughing at the subject anyways
yeah so so how did learning see was
tough because C is not like C++ where it
can be object-oriented but it's not it's
just we use what's called pointers and
these pointers are used to reference
data inside an address so we can pull
manipulate things using these pointers
but for some reason they in C they
decided that like these pointers mean
[__] like every different thing ever
and it's just it's it's built for
masochists basically it was just
terrible I don't know it was just so
[__] hard but it's a step that you
have to like learn yeah yeah because
it's it's so important because your
MacBook is is a linux-based so it runs C
code a lot of the Linux systems like
almost like majority of what we use in
this world is Linux based like even that
supercomputer that summit supercomputer
is ran off of Linux you move out that's
so weird crazy right so are we good on
time we're good on time what's I mean we
can give it 15 20 more minutes yeah so
10 15 or something
I think I'm think I'm at the end of kind
of what I haven't wanted to talk about
like becoming touch it a good basis well
it's just like chill on it what did you
do
what got you into like science math like
is there any way oh yeah whether it was
childhood or teenagers or anything that
like kept you hooked do you remember um
I felt like I was always good I always
felt like I was okay with math like I
never like you know of course I wasn't
the kid that like I say that I am but I
was never the kid that got none first
with those multiplication tables nothing
like grad school like you would like you
would slam just to make people know that
you were done first like so lamb that
[__] you're like I didn't do the
last 37 I'm done first [__] anyways I
think well at a very young age I've
always always liked space I've always
wanted to be an astronaut and if you
know me I'm very well connected to the
spaceman spaceman
I am the spaceman and I think like when
I was in like fourth grade I did the I
did my science project on the Curie uh
yeah the Mars rover yeah yeah so I
became a little Elon Musk like follower
at that point in time because I'm like
you were just investing in PayPal
exactly mom my mom I need any PayPal
wicked smart
but uh no I've always I've always I mean
I still want to be a [__] astronaut
man [__] but um
never lose your dinosaur right like [__]
bro I mean I don't really know how it's
gonna work out but we are doing some
interesting stuff with the moon and yes
space the space is gonna be a pretty
open thing and I think China's going
back to the moon you believe that it's
50 50 years later we're going we're
going back there man great opens its
rips open this whole new like weird
world it's exciting but it's cool that
we're going behind
yeah I think the next the next thing
that actually got me into computers so
you can actually is you take a milk
carton yeah you can take a milk carton
and you can be becomes this computer
where it has like flashcards
and you I think what you do is you pick
up you pick up the flashcard and it like
goes into the milk carton and it's it it
flips the card around it's basically
what it does because the answer is on
the back so there's you have a have a
five by five or yeah the five by three
note card with a question in front of it
and then you put it in the computer and
the computer spits it back to you I
think you'd read it to them so yeah so I
think like just that's exactly where I
was like [__] I love technology
technology is cool like I want to do
this like but as I went along like you
know I got through high school and
became a very active deca member I think
that's that's the initially where I met
you with you in gunner oh hey maybe both
trying to recruit you guys into deca
and I'm glad I did and by yes
yeah is from that opportunity oh great I
think anybody dude it's like one of the
more important thing I think like
anybody if you can get your little
sister little brothers listener into
deca if they're in high school marketing
program it gives you great interview
experience a lot of mark mock like
interviews and stuff that's a great
stuff for dude it's so crazy too because
like a Rick Davis shot Rick Davis you're
the man he I feel very blessed to have
been under his era of deca but I crazy
enough like I was I was doing a wedding
this summer and I met one of the actual
the new instructor for that class like
oh I don't know like how it came up or
like like I don't know if I just asked
you do like you know just just being
nice kills you know yeah hey woody oh
I'm the I'm the new marketing director
or instructor for Kelso high school
mm-hmm no [__] you don't say Wow and so
I mean that's some shoes to fill yeah
that is something I was like dude you
the exact exact same ones I'd like to
get some shoes all right second here in
that time
think about that like a short joke right
yeah yeah so
yeah I got into I got in the deca and I
was thinking how much I'm just gonna be
a business guy I'm gonna be a business
guy and I can't sell [__] I worse I am
the [__] worst salesman ever like I
can't do anything I'm not you know shout
out like the Justin lappam's of the
world who can just hustle yeah I love I
love that guy because you can just
hustle I do that's and that is not my
forte I like I like pushing numbers and
so that I was like oh you know well
maybe it got me thinking I was like yo I
like I like numbers
I've always liked numbers I I don't know
why like I was really good in math in
high school but I've always liked number
so you know I still like business and
select numbers so I'll getting to
accounting and then I quickly found out
with accounting that accounting is just
the same [__] over and over so sorry I
don't any my accounting majors yeah I
love you guys what you guys do is very
important it really is but it's it's
getting a bang the chemistry is not
there yeah for kills it's not there hey
you tested the waters it wasn't for you
I'm um I'm a problem-solver dude that
does one of my Forte's is I can look at
things and go I need this I need this I
need this and we're gonna make this all
stitch together and we're gonna come up
with the solution and that's that's what
I do best
seriously what I do best and Counting
plugging numbers carry things I mean
laughs I it there hold it no it's it's
it's not just plugging numbers it's it's
balancing the books it's creating
Ledger's it's all that kind of stuff
whereas in it hasn't changed the
practice of accounting has not changed
in the Roman era it has not changed I
swear to God
so you didn't do you didn't do deca or
you didn't do Salesman yeah I decided
that was just like yeah but then okay so
my buddy shout out my buddy Evan
Anderson who I met up in Bellingham
he and I work together at Lowe's he was
in the lumber area and I was in the
paint desk and I think we we became
friends through music obviously like we
both really liked heavy-metal lunch and
all that stuff and Evan was in the
computer science program and he was he
was a senior year and he was he was on
his way out and I think we were just
like [__] both jumped one night and
Evan goes dude why don't you [__] do
this [__] like you seem like you've got
like such a knack at it like why don't
you do this with me like you say you
don't like you're in [__] major right
now dude [__] switch that [__] up man
right he was he was like dude I think
you'd be [__] great at this
you really think yeah yeah and I just go
haven't you're just so [__] smart
ladies like to date doesn't have
anything to [__] do with that right
he's like you're more than [__]
capable Kelly right and I have to have
to say this with people is whenever I
bring up what I'm doing and I had hate
when people get discouraged I hate it I
hate when people look at math and they
just go [__] dude yeah it's a million
it's a million steps though they don't
see that one staircase the one step yeah
we just see the million steps they don't
want to do it and that's like I've
climbed the mountain did I have I'm not
like there's still some [__] that's out
there that's just any yeah like I won't
I won't probably touch on because I just
don't need I do want to get my minor in
mathematics and there's like analysis
and stuff like a couple other stuff that
I want to I want to take before I'm like
I cash out I'm done but for the most
part I I've wanted to mount indeed I've
I've done every branch of mathematics
possible and it's beautiful at the top
it's just you look up you've returned
back it's just it's so beautiful how the
world and the universe works and so like
yeah I looked I think I went to like
best or no I went to office max one day
and I was like
I need a calculator because I think my
TA a3 was [__] up on me or something
and I just needed just a simple
calculator here's the weird thing about
calculus is that you don't need like
some crazy-ass TI a3 all he needs like a
little punch number calculator that's it
I think I needed something that could
compute like angles of sine so there
sine and cosine tangent [__] like that I
needed to figure out how are the angle
of [__] I don't know what I was doing at
the time but I was like [__] dude like
do you realize that you can unlock the
universe with this little [__] thing
if you understand those answers fit into
other places they do it's so crazy
that's right
but yeah it's the truth it is the
[__] truth and it's like this little
10 10 dollar thing if you know how it
works it unlocks everything yeah
everything nuts dude fastening dude I
always love that I've mentioned that on
this podcast before that I think
mathematics is exactly that beautiful
I think mathematics is beautiful I the
cool thing about me is like I mean we've
been friends for a long time you know I
I don't know a ton about math I it
interests me I love it I think it's
fascinating I love to learn about it I'm
kind of like I love to learn a little
bit about everything you know yes but of
course but I like it's funny growing up
I always have that I'm not good at math
I'm a good I'll write a mean paper I'll
read anything you need me to out loud
I'm great at all that stuff but when it
comes to math and chemistry got thrown
into that math thing too because I I hit
a point in chemistry where I was like I
stopped understanding the stage before
this fully and now that I've gone to the
other Saders I can't understand any of
what they're saying and so I was like no
no that's math too that all sucks but
now that I'm older it you know I learned
little bits and pieces and like we you
know you and I always have good
conversations you teach me a ton just by
us being our friendship but like it
excites me to think genuinely like later
in my life when I have like let's say
some free time like what's a subject I
want to dive into you know I've got a
lot that I'd like to dive into but I'm
literally like later in life I'm
definitely gonna spend you know maybe a
year to I'm just learning more math I'm
so excited about that I think it's such
a beautiful wonderful thing I think
again that like just you two said
it's not daunting it's not you know big
picture it's a ton right Bo but the
first step it looks like this is
interesting science is interesting math
is interesting physics interesting like
you can you can take a little step and
you can flirt with and you can learn a
little bit oh yeah yeah and yeah it's
becomes like I think I got to a lot of
these these higher level math classes
they have this aha moment where you're
like you're fighting with it you're
fighting with it you're fighting with it
you're like God like this doesn't make
sense like and so your brain is a muscle
right you have to give it time to button
[__] sink in and and think about it and
sleep on it and then come back to and be
like oh and then finally I think it was
um differential equations which is
[__] god-awful it's just it but it
still it was at one point in time I mean
for me obviously for those level of
classes it's not that I think calc for
was a little bit harder for me because
it was just coming back to all the
things that I've done previously but I'm
usually good at something isn't hard for
me until like I have to get as I give
something time time and space and to
just kind of let that let that kind of
sink in and do its thing and and work on
it I can I can get it right and finally
at some point in different that
differential Espace everything just
started falling in together like all of
all these pieces that we were learning
about it just all fell in so write
beautifully together and like I was just
like I [__] love math I love it like
this is why this shit's [__]
beautiful is cuz [__] like that happens
right and yeah I agree with you it [__]
clicks into place and it opens up new
doorways that you didn't know existed
and so it's just very fulfilling thing
like wait this is an answer that works
what yeah so look at like this
Oilers equation our euler's boilers
boilers you really don't know this guy
describe what it is to somebody who's
not saying okay so it is the coefficient
e to ^ imaginary I times pi and then it
continues equation plus 1 equals 0 and
why you that why this equation is so
[__] mind-blowing is that E is an
irrational number it's like two point
seven on and on and on and on because it
when you grew it when you graph e it I
think it starts at negative negative one
and then it goes up like that and it
just goes on and on and on and on up and
up but if it looks like it plateaus but
it does it okay so you're taking one
irrational number you're taking an
imaginary number and then you're taking
PI which is another irrational number so
you're taking you need to tell me that
two rational numbers and then you take
one to the power of it and then at an
imaginary one number plus one equals
zero yeah and it works itself out or
even that or if you take or if you take
this this a little bit and then minus
one to the other side of the equation
you tell me that e to the I times pi
equals negative one that's [__] nuts
to back that [__] just works well it's
so cool because you see it at first and
you're like what the [__] are you
talking about but then like if you just
if you just give it time like you said
give it time let somebody there explain
it to you or a lot of times like like
yard work I'm a huge fan of yard work I
love yard work in a lot of times it's
like you can learn something Friday
Saturday Sunday cram right you've been
cramming you you're in I mean I'm down
here I'm learning about a lot of [__]
and then during the week Monday through
Friday I've been doing yard work here
and there wah but in the back of my mind
asked him doing yard work I'm thinking
about grass something about emptying my
grass bag but in the back of my mind
these equations and how I understand
these these things in mathematics or in
the subject are working on it and
sometimes you'll have these like
aha moments yes like holy [__] yeah like
you hear like you like the bag gets full
in your lawnmower dies and for some
reason that sound
sparks you're like oh my god I give the
[__] equations dude this is perfect
this is perfect hit me with it okay so I
wasn't I was actually gonna first start
with this story but now that we've
gotten to it excellent oh yes this is so
great okay so this dude his name is
Archimedes he's a pull up pull up
it wasn't philosopher he was a
mathematician kind of guy and he lived
in Syracuse in 250 BCE like 250 before
Christ was born she liked that so way
back in the day right way back in the
day and he's a smart guy wicked smart
right
um and one day that he lived in Syracuse
back in Greece and the King apparently
had given this goldsmith or he was a
newly appointed King and he wanted a
crown so he said okay I want to I want a
lot this much of gold to this gold Smith
to make me a crown and the Goldsmith was
like all right I'll make you a crown and
I'll give it back so the goldsmith went
may has a crown gave it back to King and
all was well until King started hearing
some rumors that [__] ain't all gold man
yeah yeah yeah yeah so disrespect yeah I
know right like so like the gold like
the he was like you know did that
goldsmith just like hack off like half
this gold and like put a bunch because
silver is like also very malleable and
like you can actually combine it with
coal and becomes kind of goldish in a
way I think but uh I don't know I'm not
an alchemist but anyways the the King
goes Archimedes because Archimedes is
kind of like this [__] brilliant did
it goes he's dude like I heard like this
Goldsmith it like ripped me off like I
don't know if like he's like like took
off with his gold and made an extra coin
off of it kind of thing like
is there any way you can improve like
because it looks it looks like a like
normal gold crown thing like but how can
I look how can I prove that is so
Archimedes he's like all right let me
think about it
right so our Khomeini's thought about it
and the the classic story goes he was in
the bathtub homie was in the bathtub and
the the coin the term Eureka is from him
so apparently this [__] dude he
figured it out he goes he goes Eureka
and the homie like got out of the
bathtub and she's like streak down the
roads of Syracuse to the King like butt
ass naked just [__] going he's like I
got it I got it I got it like I figured
it out and it had to do with the bathtub
so the the in physics the buoyancy is
the force the buoyant force of an object
is the same as the the weight of the
water the volume of water I know that's
the tricky right okay so I'll say that
again so the the force the buoyant force
is equal to the displacement of the
volume of water so so the weight of the
object on the top of the surface of the
water pushes ya so if it yeah so that
that gold will try and be be buoyant so
what happened so what Archimedes figure
this out he goes okay I need exactly as
much as much gold as you gave him
because they have like vlogs and [__]
back mind they like okay King King gave
him this much gold so what he did
Archimedes did he goes he had a scale
right and then he had like two tubs of
water you know so what he did was he put
the crown on one scale and then he put
the same amount of gold on the other
scale and he submerged them so that they
floated and so if the if the crown was
good all good
it would have been equal in the middle
but it wasn't it so yeah dude yeah like
the so
ended up happening was like the
obviously the the I think the silver was
lighter than gold and so the scales was
was off and so the King was like [__]
that actually is because he put up he
goes okay but it's [__] yeah her head
so what cuz you put you put the two same
amounts of gold on each side of the
scale and then dip them in the water
that they'll be equal right so he was
like yo if that if that scales off which
it was by a long shot
it he was [__] he was like there's you
mix this with other [__] and you [__]
took the rest of the world and made off
with it so [__] off of that
[__] head so hopefully that
dude had skipped town he's like before
they figure this out no before they
measure away to no way yeah
so yeah it's that it's that aha moment
is that arica so yeah you know I think
this this is a good way to wrap it up
man I think that you know kind of a lot
would I would I do lessening the the
input sometimes there's a lot of a lot
of a good thing to do like so we're
learning all week you're learning a lot
of times we're stuffing our brains and
blah blah blah
stuffing and stuff and again sometimes
the best ideas come when you're mowing
your lawn or you're in the bathtub and
and these ideas can't come when you're
constantly just trying to shove down
more ideas right so when you're
constantly taking information
information information whether that's
could be good information could be like
I'm so fascinated by everything that I
just want to click on every YouTube
video that I see I know that all the
time but but I I do well now being able
to like keep my my brain working in the
background keep my brain my subconscious
mind doing the scientific method for me
sort of figuring [__] out you know as
I'm mowing the lawn as I'm in the
bathroom waiting for my Eureka moment so
listener take some breaks definitely
allow yourself some room for Eureka
moments you know know what might we
might pop up that debug debug yourself
you bug yourself yeah if this the net if
that's not just figure it out Kelly I
love you bro it's been a pleasure to
talk I'm glad that you got to come and
talk about yeah
you know some some things that you know
about I feel like I learned a little bit
more today than than I do I always
learned something wanna talk to you I
hope you guys aren't lost if anything if
you guys like or like well what did kill
you mean by that
just talk to me oh yeah I'll explain it
so yeah yeah I'm glad I'm grateful for
you
I hope you have a good rest your day
listeners and I hope you enjoyed Kelly
I'm sure she'll he'll be on in the
future we'll talk about some more
complex stuff try to simplify it
cheers have a good rest day
you